[SPEAKER_00]: So, the question is, why should I meditate?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's clearly something that a person can be asking oneself, regardless of how long you have been meditating before, whether you're just starting or you've been doing it for years.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's good to remind yourself
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I mean, you could, you know, you can provide an answer for it, or you could use it as a reflexive tool, that question of, why should I meditate?
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you know why you should meditate,
[SPEAKER_00]: You can only benefit from reviewing your mind and re-establishing the right context for... the right context and the clarity of the purpose of meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the thing here.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you go and meditate, you can ask yourself, for example, why am I meditating?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why am I doing this?
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't just sit and do
[SPEAKER_00]: And go through motions of various techniques, but actually ask yourself, what is my motivation for doing this in the first place?
[SPEAKER_00]: What am I trying to achieve?
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, obviously, depending on the answer there, your reflection can go in various directions.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, for example, one of the obvious answers would be freedom from suffering,
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, for example, less specific, but equally valid, would be peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: So many, everybody, everybody values peace, mental peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, probably one of the most common reasons for people turning to meditation is because they want to be able to develop a peaceful mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you know, you can
[SPEAKER_00]: You can go into some sort of half-awake absorptions, that can then approximate a peaceful feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even that, it's not a guarantee that you're always going to get it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you sit through, like, and watch the tip of your nose, and do a mechanical technique of concentration and so on, sometimes you might result in a peaceful feeling, but sometimes you won't.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, instead of just taking that for granted, you should investigate it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is it that sometimes I'm peaceful, sometimes I'm not?
[SPEAKER_00]: Can I be peaceful at will, at my own will?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why do I have to rely on going through certain motions of my meditation techniques, so that it will result in a peaceful feeling?
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it possible to directly
[SPEAKER_00]: Think peace and be peaceful by thinking peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the good news is, it is possible, but the bad news is, it's in a complete opposite direction from where meditation techniques are usually taking you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, instead of just mechanically observing bodily sensations and similar things, you should really investigate the clarity of purpose behind
[SPEAKER_00]: Behind your present sort of technique and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, develop like a peripheral context.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, all you need to do is think about it and that context is there established.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you think about it rightly, it means you partake in that context.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if the context is context of peace, all you need to do is fully understand what that context is and you will be peaceful, regardless of the
[SPEAKER_00]: of the technique, regardless of the circumstances and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can use it as a reflection.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can ask yourself, okay, so I'm meditating because I want to be peaceful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do I know what peace is?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or maybe, don't even necessarily imply whether you know or not, just ask yourself, what is peace for me?
[SPEAKER_00]: What do I think peace is?
[SPEAKER_00]: How would I describe peace?
[SPEAKER_00]: If somebody comes here and asks me, what is peace?
[SPEAKER_00]: What would I tell them?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not necessarily right or wrong answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just, eh... how would you designate it in your own words to someone else?
[SPEAKER_00]: How would you convey it?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, you can dwell on that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not...
[SPEAKER_00]: I keep repeating this, because there's obviously a tendency in every mind to jump on to... to, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Looking for a right answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: But this is... this is more like a descriptive method, describing what's already there, and through doing so, developing clarity in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there isn't really a right or wrong answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's right if you're aiming in the right direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: It isn't right based on the content of your answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as long as you're questioning it rightly, it's right, even if you don't necessarily say the right words.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because whatever you use to designate the peaceful feeling at the time, it is standing for it in that designation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it is something that corresponds to what you're experiencing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're learning how to think concretely, think what is present, without overdoing, without underdoing, without negating the presence of that peaceful feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you get to understand it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see the nature of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nature of it that it has arisen, that it's enduring on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by seeing that, you get to see then the attitudes that you have been exercising in regard to that independent feeling, be it pleasant, unpleasant or neutral, peaceful feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: And only by seeing that, you can realize that that's where the problem was.
[SPEAKER_00]: It wasn't that you were not experiencing peace on the level of feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was like
[SPEAKER_00]: Even when you were experiencing peace on the level of feeling, you were not peaceful because of your attitude towards your own feelings, attitudes of craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for as long as you don't understand what the feeling is, you don't see the extent of the feeling, you're not going to see the extent of your own craving in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, think about how would you designate a peaceful feeling?
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if it's... even if you're not necessarily peaceful,
[SPEAKER_00]: How would you designate a peaceful feeling as a goal of your meditation?
[SPEAKER_00]: What would it be?
[SPEAKER_00]: Would it be like a non-disturbance?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: What constitutes disturbance then?
[SPEAKER_00]: Clarify that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't jump into the answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let your thoughts endure a bit.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once you ask a question, let it sort of persist.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't let your mind forget about it, but don't over-focus on it either.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what constitutes disturbance?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is disturbance?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is in common to every disturbance that you have ever experienced in your life?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's in common is that it is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Always.
[SPEAKER_00]: Something would have not been designated as disturbance if it were pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no such thing as pleasant disturbance.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it's pleasant, it's not then disturbing you, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: So then,
[SPEAKER_00]: The disturbance is always unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then you can ask yourself the next question.
[SPEAKER_00]: If... would it be possible, for example, to experience disturbance but not suffer on account of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then again, you can you can reflect on that and see that there were
[SPEAKER_00]: Instances in the past, I'm sure, whereby disturbing things, things that used to make you suffer, they would disturb you, you would go through them, but you would not necessarily suffer or not necessarily suffer to the same extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if the suffering is truly rooted in that unpleasantness of this... of a disturbance, means you would always suffer to the same extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just... you wouldn't be... you wouldn't be even self-aware of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Suffering would have been part of the disturbance.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the fact that disturbance is there, but then suffering, sometimes it's like, sometimes it's to some extent, sometimes there isn't any, means there is something else there, that causes that suffering, because if it were truly, solely rooted in circumstantial disturbances, you would be unaware of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, disturbance would, to the same extent, equal suffering always.
[SPEAKER_00]: There wouldn't be, there wouldn't be no discrepancy.
[SPEAKER_00]: And on some occasions, for example, when you're in a good mood, even some heavy, serious disturbances still don't make you suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your mood doesn't change.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if your mood is fully dependent, fully determined by the circumstances, disturbing or non-disturbing circumstances, then that mood would not persist.
[SPEAKER_00]: A good mood would not persist amidst disturbances, yet it persists, even for an ignorant mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that means that you can't
[SPEAKER_00]: Say that your suffering, your bad moods, are rooted in the circumstantial disturbances, because it doesn't always correspond to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's that realization of that discrepancy, that's what gives you... that's basically the room where the practice is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Initially, it feels very narrow, obviously, but the more you dwell on it, the wider it becomes, the more space you get.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because through reflection, you're clarifying it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you're clarifying, what I said before, your attitude in regard to the disturbing, unpleasant feeling, or a neutral, peaceful feeling, or the agreeable, pleasant feeling, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you are liable to these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: They come and go.
[SPEAKER_00]: They endure, the feelings, one at a time.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's your own attitude in regard to it that determines, then,
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether your mood will be affected or not, whether you will suffer or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, that takes us to the next question, which is, if... if you're not suffering in your mood, amidst disturbances, disagreeable disturbances, unpleasant sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, thoughts, words of others, but your mood doesn't change in some occasion,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, is it then right to say that absence of... that basically peace is found in non-disturbance of the environment?
[SPEAKER_00]: Wouldn't be more accurate saying peace is then found in non-disturbance of your mood?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you could see how first we started from disturbing environment, non-disturbing environment, but now you realize that it's actually your mood in regard to the environment.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where your suffering is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if there is no suffering on the level of your mood, it doesn't matter the environment.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're imperturbable in regard to the environment.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now you can take that another step further from the world onto the mind, mood of your mind, but now you can apply the same principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, reflect upon a question.
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you in charge of your own moods?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do your moods originate at your will?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or do they arise on their own, cease on their own, and endure on their own, for as long as they want to endure?
[SPEAKER_00]: The answer is quite obvious, but that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't necessarily rush in giving that answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Allow this question to endure, because question forces you to look at the answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Answering it, makes you look at something else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Letting question endure, it's sort of pushing in the direction of the answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, am I in control of my moods?
[SPEAKER_00]: Ask that question, let it endure then.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't jump at answering, but don't ignore it either.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whichever my mood is currently present, am I the creator of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I in charge?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if it were to cease, can I prevent it from doing so?
[SPEAKER_00]: If it were to increase, can I prevent it from doing so?
[SPEAKER_00]: You realize it's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's really just not dwelling long enough on the nature of this being inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you sort of ignore it and then start acting out of belief as if the mood is yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the mood is... it's a container of your experience, a particular coloring to it, a particular weather to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: What you do within that, as in choices you make and intentions upon which you act, that's on you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the container of the weather, it's pretty much on the level of those circumstantial disturbances or non-disturbances.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, through reflecting like this, you started with a disturbance comes from the world, then, oh, well, disturbance actually comes from the mood, and now you realize, oh, disturbance doesn't even come from the mood, because mood is not in my control.
[SPEAKER_00]: Disturbance comes from my choices and my intentions,
[SPEAKER_00]: In regard to the mood I'm experiencing, in regard to the feeling I'm experiencing... And that's why the Buddha would often sum up his entire teaching by don't do anything that's rooted in unwholesome, as in don't act out of intentions that are based on greed, aversion, delusion, and act upon intentions that are based on non-greed, non-aversion, non-delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: That will purify your mind whether you want it or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: But see, you can be acting good and all proper, but if you still hold the view that the root of your suffering is in the world, or in the mood, or in all sorts of things, but in your choices, means you're still... everything you do, whether good or bad, is undermined, underlined by the wrong view.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's really why you should be meditating.
[SPEAKER_00]: To abandon the wrong view and develop peace on account of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, your meditation will be about maintaining that wholesome peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, as we just clarified, disturbance, the peace, or absence of peace, does not come from the external disturbances, doesn't even come from your moods.
[SPEAKER_00]: It comes from your own craving, perpetuated by your desire and lust and intentions, in regard to the moods that are persisting.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in a bad mood,
[SPEAKER_00]: your actions will be revolving around denying it, trying to get rid of it, your mind will be occupied by that, it will be rooted in that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Good mood, again, your mind will be overly welcoming it, overly indulging it, overly binding itself to it, as in, oh, this is mine, this is great, it will last forever.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in the neutral mood, which in itself it's actually what the peace is, neutral feeling, neutral mood, the mind
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the mind turns towards anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anything that will cause it to feel.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anything other than that neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, in itself, that neutral feeling is unpleasant with the mind that still has the habits of ignoring.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's unpleasant in as much as boredom is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: That results in anxiety that is very unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the
[SPEAKER_00]: The neutral... the neutral mood is something that can be... well, your actions in regard to the neutral mood is something that can be gradually cultivated, to the point of where you stop resisting the neutral mood, stop trying to distract yourself from it, and only then you can get to recognize the peace within that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why Buddha said the neutral feeling is unpleasant when it's unknown,
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, if you recognize that you yourself is not free, you're not free from ignorance,
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to be careful in taking what you think peace is for granted.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the only true way of knowing what peaceful is, is to abandon ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Peace is pleasant when it's known, when it's understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you know that you haven't necessarily made any significant understanding that you can explain to yourself or even others,
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, here you are, chasing a certain standard of peace that you assumed, means you're most likely going to be acting out of sensuality and craving towards pleasant feeling, which, for you, it's peaceful.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, nobody's... like, I'm not saying that there is no peaceful feeling even for Pārthujana.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is, but he should not take it for granted as that which truly peaceful is, because it isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: The true peace is when ignorance is abandoned.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not when circumstances are suppressed and controlled and managed and measured.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's when the mind cannot be disturbed amidst the disturbances.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what peace is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the only way for mind to not be disturbed amidst disturbances is through understanding what truly disturbance is or where the disturbance truly comes from.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when you recognize that it comes from your gratuitous attitude,
[SPEAKER_00]: of assuming ownership of your moods, of your environment, of your circumstances, of your senses, then you will stop doing it, because it becomes... like understanding that this is not in your control, becomes incompatible with a behavior that assumes control of those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't have to then make an extra effort to stop assuming.
[SPEAKER_00]: Automatically, your behavior will change, because you have uprooted the assumption upon which it was based.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the peaceful feeling is then, when there is absence of craving...
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry, the peace is when there is absence of craving in regard to what's being felt at the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you sit down and meditate, as we just done with this whole reflection, self-reflection, self-interrogation, as the Buddha would often be encouraging monks to do, you realize that you are at peace,
[SPEAKER_00]: Not when there are no disturbances externally or bad moods internally.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're at peace when there is no craving in regard to the disagreeable feeling, whether disagreeable of the bad mood or disagreeable of the environment.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there will be no craving in regard to disagreeable when you fully understand the disagreeable, agreeable and neutral as a reason on its own, which is another word saying impermanent, not created by me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: On its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: Circumstantially it endures.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't need to rush and get rid of its presence.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can allow it to endure because it does not concern me.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it will stop concerning you when you fully understand that it cannot concern you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it cannot concern you when you fully understand that it has arisen on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it all revolves around the same principles, same understanding of the same universal natures of phenomena.
[SPEAKER_00]: In this case, feelings and states of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, if you want to cultivate peace, you just have to cultivate indifference towards presently enduring moods, presently enduring feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you cultivate indifference sufficiently,
[SPEAKER_00]: To the sufficient extent, you will basically stop perpetuating your craving through negligent acts that were rooted in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that is truly peaceful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then you wouldn't be afraid, even of things that used to cause you anxieties or fears or bad moods and so on, because you are above your moods now as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: The weather still comes and goes and changes,
[SPEAKER_00]: But none of that affects your intentions and the clarity of your vision, of your mindfulness, of your understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if the mind can establish itself upon the context of peace that we just described, it can do so at will.
[SPEAKER_00]: The clearer the context becomes, the easier your meditation and mental establishment is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why monks who have been properly developed, they would say, oh, I can obtain jhānas at will.
[SPEAKER_00]: Literally, you will them, they're there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they are the context, the peripheral context, that transcend the domain of sensuality, ill-will, even thinking and pondering, in the second jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: The movement of the thoughts, even that, you go beyond.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's all through clarifying
[SPEAKER_00]: Deep peripheral context of your currently present situation and currently enduring feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are not many enduring at the same time.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's always one at a time, on that general level.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, we're back where we started.
[SPEAKER_00]: Non-disturbance, then, is what peace is.
[SPEAKER_00]: is what absence of craving in regard to your current situation is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's something you can see, that that context can... you can develop, even when you're not necessarily sitting cross-legged and meditating.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can stay at the back of your mind, even when you're going around walking, extending your arms, eating, going to a toilet, as the Buddha many times described.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said the monkey enters jhāna, or no, actually, I think he was talking about himself.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said he would enter jhāna, and that state would be so divine,
[SPEAKER_00]: His mind will be established upon the divine.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then he said, whether he walks, sits down, eats, sweeps, goes to the toilet, whatever he does in that state, it's also divine, because the mind is established upon the divine state of jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Divine meaning lofty, meaning transcended the central base, transcended the concern with the senses, transcended the intentions rooted in the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the only way to do that is to fully understand what those intentions are.
[SPEAKER_00]: To fully recognize the domain of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you go beyond.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this is how you do it, as we've just done it, through self-questioning.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because each time you ask the question, even if your question is not necessarily very accurate, at least it's turning you in the direction you should be going.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, what is underneath this, that I'm doing right now?
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, questioning is forcing you to become self-aware, without making that self-awareness into another thing you're doing mechanically, because that's the point you want to avoid.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mechanical repetition of your meditation technique.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mindlessness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why am I meditating?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I want peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do I have to wait for that peace, then?
[SPEAKER_00]: If the sole basis for peace is absence of craving right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you don't.
[SPEAKER_00]: All you need to do is stop craving right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_00]: You stop craving by realizing the things you crave in regard to are indifferent to your own craving, makes no difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, your craving becomes redundant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't intentionally stop craving, but you can certainly, through discernment of what you are craving in regard to, you can evaporate it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can stop feeding your craving and it will wither away through that repetitive effort of re-clarifying that which you already know.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then you just remind yourself or something else can remind you things that you used to crave.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once you abandon craving, those things arise and there is no craving and it reminds you that you are free from craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you're an arahant, it reminds you that you're completely free from craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, I think there was somewhere in the suttas, where...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think somebody asked the Buddha whether the arahant constantly experienced pleasure of enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said, no, initially.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then that becomes, you know, he gets used to it, it becomes normal, and then he would experience it whenever things that used to cause the defilements to arise, he would encounter them in the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, it would remind him that there are no defilements that used to arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's just like a memory of, oh, you remember how you used to be and now you realize you're incapable.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're incapable of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're incapable of craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're incapable of lusting.
[SPEAKER_00]: Incapable of having aversion and ill-will.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that reminder reminds you, comes with that pleasure as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether you're doing walking meditation, sitting meditation, especially if you still don't have the right view, you really want to be aiming at that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Clarifying the context of your actions and then discerning the basis upon which you gratuitously maintain the attitude of craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: I want more of this, I want less of that, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that will result in peace, in mental
[SPEAKER_00]: Eh, eko nimitī.